James B. Christoph papers, 1959-1998 C417
Indiana University Archives
James B. Christoph papers
1959-1998
Indiana University Archives
Christoph, James B. (James Bernard)
C417
4 cubic feet 6 boxes
James B. Christoph served as professor of political science and West European studies from 1967 until retiring with emeritus status in 1990. His main area of interest was British politics; much of his research, publications, and other professional activities were focused on this topic. Included in this collection is correspondence, teaching materials, faculty annual reports, and other items pertaining to his professional interests and activities, such as conference presentations.
Access Restrictions
Select files containing recommendations and student evaluations are closed to researchers at this time.
Biographical Note
Born on August 17, 1928 in Waukesha, Wisconsin, James B. Christoph graduated with highest honors from the University of Wisconsin in 1950. He received his doctorate in political science from the University of Minnesota in 1956. In 1955, Christoph joined the Ohio State University political science faculty and eventually served as Assistant Dean of Arts and Sciences. He later earned a faculty appointment for the 1966-1967 academic year from John Hopkins University at that university's Bologna Center in Bologna, Italy. He then came to Indiana University in 1967 as the chairman of the Department of Political Science, a position he retained until 1971. In 1973, he began a one year term as the chairperson of the West European Studies Program. He continued to teach courses in political science and West European studies until his retirement in 1990.
Christoph's research was focused on increasing the understanding of government politics and the society of post-World War II Britain. He authored and contributed to many books and articles on these topics, including two of his most recognized works, Capital Punishment and British Politics and The Mandarins of Western Europe, a book for which he served as editor. Led by his interest in British politics, he played a key role in the founding of the British Politics Group. He was president of this group from 1979-1980.
Other accomplishments in his career include receiving Indiana University's Distinguished Teaching Award in 1980 and the Faculty Service award in 1988. He died in May 1998 at the age of 69, and was survived by his wife Natalie Kunz and their 5 children.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into three series: Correspondence, Teaching and professional activities, and Subject files.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of James B. Christoph span the years from 1959-1998 and are organized into three series: Correspondence, Teaching and professional activities, and Subject files.
The Correspondence series includes correspondence spanning the period from 1961-1998, some of which predates Christoph's time at Indiana University. The bulk of this correspondence is arranged by year, though a portion of it is arranged alphabetically by subject. The correspondents and topics within the correspondence vary widely, but recurrent subjects include: publications and editorial comments, research projects, and political science and West European studies department matters. There are also many letters from Christoph's students and former students. Student evaluations and recommendations written by Christoph have been removed from the correspondence folders and are restricted.
The next series, Teaching and professional activities, is dated 1962-1996. It is further organized into 3 subseries, which are Course materials and notes, Faculty annual reports and Academic projects and lectures. Items in the Course materials and notes subseries are dated 1969-1996 and are arranged alphabetically by course title or folder heading and consist of Christoph's lecture notes, exam questions, syllabi, and other handouts for the students. Materials containing student grades have been removed from these folders. Included in the second subseries, Faculty annual reports, are Christoph's annual reports from 1967-1995. These describe in detail his professional activities and accomplishments. Many of the folders also include evidence of these activities and accomplishments, such as letters and announcements. Dated 1962-1996, the Academic projects and lectures subseries contains materials pertaining to conference and seminar presentations and reviews of his book Capital Punishment and British Politics. Also included are correspondence and interview notes for a research project which explored changes in the outlook and roles of senior British civil servants in the late 1980s.
The Subject files series spans the years 1959-1996 and is arranged alphabetically by folder heading. This small series includes items on varying topics, such as political pamphlets and fliers from British parliamentary elections and materials collected by Christoph about the National Endowment for the Arts.
Separated Material
One photo of Christoph and other organizers of a 1966 conference in Bologna, Italy has been transferred to the University Archives Photograph Collection.
Related Material
Additional publications and research materials may be accessed in IUScholarworks: http://scholarworks.iu.edu/
Acquisition Information
Accession Information: 2010/097
Provenance
Gift of Natalie Christoph, 2010.
Appraisal
Materials listing student grades have been removed and destroyed.
Political scientists --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Political science --Study and teaching (Higher) --Indiana --Bloomington.; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Political Science -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Christoph, James B. (James Bernard) -- Archives; Christoph, James B. (James Bernard) -- Correspondence; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Political Science -- Faculty -- Archives; Indiana University, Bloomington. West European Studies -- Faculty -- Archives; Indiana University, Bloomington. West European Studies -- History -- 20th century -- Sources
- Correspondence, 1961-1998; undated (Box 1)
  - 1963 (Box 1)
  - 1964 (Box 1)
  - 1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1967 (Box 1)
  - 1968 (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970 (Box 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972 (Box 1)
  - 1973, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1974, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1975, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1976 (Box 1)
  - 1977, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1978, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1979, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1980, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1981, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1982, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1983, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1984 (Box 2)
  - 1985 (Box 2)
  - 1986, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1987, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1988, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1989, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1990, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1991 (Box 3)
  - 1992, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1993 (Box 3)
  - 1994, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1997 (Box 3)
  - 20th Century British State proposal, 1995-1998 (Box 3)
  - American Academics, 1970-1981; undated (Box 3)
  - Bologna Center, 1965-1967 (Box 3)
    General
    (photograph removed)
  - Britain Trip, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Capital Punishment and British Politics, 1961-1969 (Box 3)
  - English Academics, 1969-1983 (Box 3)
  - Gellar Review Committee, 1969-1975 (Box 3)
  - Joel Allen Suspension, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Little, Brown and Company, 1961-1983 (Box 3)
  - Political Science (General), 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - Political Science Department, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
  - Promotion and tenure, 1968-1970; 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - Publications, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
  - Wilton Park, 1975-1983 (Box 3)
- Teaching and professional activities, 1962-1996; undated (Box 3)
  - Course materials and notes, 1969-1996; undated (Box 3)
    - British Politics (Y331), 1992; undated; (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Comparative Political Executives (Y657), 1992; undated (Box 3)
    - A Comparative Study of Canadian Parties (Y657), 1973-1988; undated (Box 3)
    - Introduction to Comparative Politics (Y107), 1991-1992; undated; (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Exam questions, 1969-1991 (Box 3)
    - London Seminar (Y401), 1989 (Box 3)
    - Mini University course, 1996; undated (Box 3)
    - Political Science courses, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - Western European Politics (Y335), 1992; undated; (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Faculty annual reports, 1967-1995 (Box 4)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 4)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 4)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 4)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 4)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 4)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 4)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 4)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 4)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 4)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 4)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 4)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 4)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 4)
    - 1986 (Box 4)
    - 1987 (Box 4)
    - 1988 (Box 4)
    - 1989 (Box 4)
    - 1990 (Box 4)
    - 1991 (Box 4)
    - 1992 (Box 4)
    - 1993 (Box 4)
    - 1994 (Box 5)
    - 1995 (Box 5)
  - Academic projects and lectures, 1962-1996; undated (Box 5)
    - Civil Service Project, 1991 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 5)
      - Notes from interviews, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Encyclopedia entry, Salem Press, 1994-1995 (Box 5)
    - European Identities conference, 1994-1996; undated (Box 5)
    - European Integration and the European Mind conference, 1992 (Box 5)
    - London talk, undated (Box 5)
    - NEH Seminar, 1981 (Box 5)
    - Presidential and Parliamentary Democracy conference, 1993 (Box 5)
    - Reviews of Capital Punishment and British Politics, 1962-1963; undated (Box 5)
- Subject files, 1959-1996; undated (Box 5)
  - British political pamphlets and fliers, 1959; 1983; undated; (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - British visit, 1994; undated (Box 6)
  - The Floyd Christoph house, undated (Box 6)
  - National Endowment for the Arts (NEA), 1978; 1993-1996 (Box 6)
  - Sunday Times guide to the election, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Restricted Materials, (1 folder) (Box 6)